All right, let's see how we could implement this function, countBlocks.
حسناً، َلنرى كيف يمكننا تنفيذ هذه الدالة، countBlocks.
It takes this integer levels as input
إنها تأخذ متغيّر العدد الصحيح levels كمُدخل
which is the number of levels the pyramid is made up of,
وهو عدد المستويات التي يتألف الهرم منها،
and returns an integer which is equal to the number of blocks it needs.
ويُرجع قيمة عدد صحيح تساوي عدد المكعّبات التي يحتاج إليها.
The first thing we need to do is declare and initialize this total variable here.
أول ما علينا فعله هو تعيين المتغيّر total وتحديد قيمته.
This will keep track of the number of blocks it needs to build
سيتتبّع عدد المكعبات التي يحتاجها بناء الهرم بالكامل
the entire pyramid by adding every level one by one.
بإضافة كل مستوى واحداً تلو الآخر.
Then, we start a loop that counts from one to the number of levels in this pyramid,
ثم ننشئ حلقة تعدّ من 1 إلى عدد مستويات ذلك الهرم،
and the increment is just i++.
وتكون الزيادة هي ++i فحسب.
Inside the loop and for each level,
داخل الحلقة ولكل مستوى،
we need to calculate the number of blocks in that level which is equal to i times i,
يجب أن نحسب عدد المكعبات في ذلك المستوى وهو يساوي i ضرب i،
because i changes from one, two,
لأن قيمة i تتغيّر من 1، إلى 2،
three, all the way until the maximum number of levels.
إلى 3، وصولاً إلى أقصى عدد من المستويات.
Once we calculate that number of what's needed for that level,
حالما نحسب عدد ما نحتاجه لذلك المستوى،
we just add it to our total variable and update total to be equal to the sum.
نضيفه إلى متغيّر total ونحدّث قيمة total لتكون مساوية للمجموع.
Finally, when the loop ends,
وأخيراً، عند نهاية الحلقة،
we just return the variable,
نعرض قيمة المتغيّر total،
Let's test it out for a three-level pyramid,
لنختبر ذلك مع هرم ذي ثلاث مستويات،
which means our input variable levels here is going to be three,
ما يعني أن قيمة المتغيّر levels التي أدخلناها ستكون 3،
total is initialized to zero,
ويتم تعيين قيمة total بصفر،
and our loop goes from one to levels which happens to be three.
وتنتقل الحلقة من 1 إلى قيمة levels وهي هنا تساوي 3.
Now let's keep track of every variable we have as we go through the loop.
لنتتبّع كل متغيّر لدينا أثناء تقدّمنا في الحلقة.
i starts by one,
تبدأ i بالعدد 1،
and then we check this condition if i is less than or equal to levels which is basically,
ثم نتحقق من هذا الشرط: i&lt;=levels،
and that is true because i is still one.
وهذا true لأن i لا تزال تساوي 1.
So we calculate the number of blocks in
فنحسب عدد المكعبات
that particular level over here which is i times i,
في ذلك المستوى تحديداً، وهي تساوي i ضرب i،
and then we add the result of i times i to total,
ثم نضيف ناتج حاصل i ضرب i إلى total،
which started as zero so makes total equal to one.
والذي قد بدأ بالقيمة صفر، وبذلك تصبح قيمة total تساوي 1.
We reached the end of the first loop, so we go back up,
وصلنا إلى نهاية الحلقة الأولى، فنعود إلى الأعلى،
add one to i, making it equal to two,
ونضيف 1 إلى i لتصبح قيمتها 2،
and then check the condition again.
ثم نتحقق من الشرط مجدداً.
Is i less than or equal to three?
هل i أقل من أو تساوي 3؟
And it's still two, so that's true.
لا تزال قيمتها تساوي 2، فهذا true.
So we calculate i times i which is two times two,
فنحسب i ضرب i، أي 2 ضرب 2،
happens to be four,
وهذا يساوي 4،
and add that to total.
ونضيف ذلك إلى total.
Total was already one,
total يساوي 1،
so we add that, making it five.
فمع إضافة 4 إليه تصبح قيمته 5.
We reached the end of this loop again so we go back up,
وصلنا إلى نهاية الحلقة مجدداً فنعود إلى الأعلى،
we add one to i, making it three.
ونضيف 1 إلى i، فتصبح قيمتها 3.
We do this check again,
نقوم بهذا التحقق مجدداً،
is three less than or equal to three?
هل 3 أقل من أو تساوي 3؟
Yes it is, because it is equal to three, so that's true.
أجل، لأن قيمتها تساوي 3، فهذا true.
So we step inside again,
فندخل مجدداً،
and calculate i times i, making it nine.
ونحسب قيمة i َضرب i، فتصبح 9.
Just three times three,
أي 3 ضرب 3،
add that to total which was five.
ونضيف ذلك إلى total، الذي كانت قيمته 5.
So that's nine plus five equals 14,
إذن 9 زائد 5 تساوي 14،
and our total gets up to 14.
وبذلك ترتفع قيمة total إلى 14.
So, we reached the end of this loop, go back up,
وهكذا وصلنا إلى نهاية هذه الحلقة، فنعود إلى أعلى،
add one more to i,
ونضيف 1 آخر إلى i،
and then we do this condition again.
ثم نتحقق من هذا الشرط مجدداً.
Is four less than or equal to three?
هل 4 أقل من أو تساوي 3؟
Nope, it's not anymore.
كلا، لم تعد i كذلك.
So we do not step into that loop anymore,
فلن ندخل إلى تلك الحلقة بعد ذلك،
and we just skip down here to return total.
فنتخطى الحلقة لنصل إلى هنا ونعرض قيمة total.
So, that not value of total at that point is 14,
إذن قيمة total عند تلك النقطة هي 14،
which is the output of this function,
وهي قيمة ناتج هذه الدالة.
that is if the input is three.
هذا في حال كانت القيمة المُدخلة هي 3.
Brilliant. You could also try to trace it
عظيم. يمكنكم أيضاً أن تجربوا تتبعها
with larger input values and see if it works for that as well.
بقيم مُدخلة أكبر لتروا إن كانت ستعمل معها أيضاً.